It's
You got it. You got it. There we go. Sorry. Okay.
Good. Okay.
Thank you, Eric.
>> And before we start, Jim Halsey, are you on? I'm
not used to this many participants,
and I've got way more than my screen is showing, so I can't tell if you're there or not. Yes,
I'm the screen with Eric. Okay, very good. So
>> we called to order the public hearing at 07:00
in the Andover Planning and Zoning Commission. We'll hold a public hearing at 7PM on 01/23/2023,
to solicit public comment and answer questions regarding
the posed amendments to its zoning regulations.
More particularly, the proposed amendments involve changes to sections five a
one and section 24 definition of
the zoning regulations so as to allow for municipal land uses
by way of special permit in the Andover rural design zone
and modify the definitions pertaining to municipal uses.
So the purpose of the public hearing the town has requested to change to allow construction of the municipal building.
This case, a community slash senior center
in the Andover Rural Design Zone by special permit.
Well, everyone knows the town
wants to put the community
center by the town hall and the school.
That's not what tonight's meeting is about.
The meeting is about having the ability by our regulations.
To put a municipal building such as a community center
in the Andover Rural Design District.
And we mentioned that it would be by special permit.
If you remember back to when we
were discussing the retail store that ended up being the Dollar General,
there was a concern that input from the town
was not being taken into consideration
in allowing the store to be built there.
And so I'm going to put up the proposed changes to the regulations in just a minute here.
But if in
that case,
you know the Dollar General was a small enough store that in the business area
we had that listed as an as of right
thing, if you will. They could build the store as of right if they met, you know, the small store conditions.
If it was a bigger store, then it would take a special permit.
And a special permit
allows us the opportunity to build something a little bit out of the ordinary in a zone,
but it allows us the opportunity to get input
from the people of the town before
making a decision on that matter.
After I get done going through the proposed regulation,
I'll invite the applicant, Eric Anderson, to make any additional comments that he would like.
Following him will be our zoning enforcement officer, Jim Halsey,
and then our attorney Mark Branch.
>> Mr.
Chairman.
Yeah go ahead. Yes for the record Mark Branch before we get into the substance of this there's one procedural item I'd like to address if I may. Okay, go ahead.
I understand you Mr. Chairman that, one member of the commission is on the community center building committee.
Another member of the commission is the spouse of a member of the Board of Education.
I don't know if that has anything to do with the matter before us. Don't think it does, but be that as it may, I did confer with town attorney Dennis O'Brien this afternoon. He and I are in agreement that that is not a conflict of interest.
The courts court cases have reviewed these things,
and, the courts recognize that in small towns the same people are on the chamber of commerce, the church board,
the boy scouts,
the little league,
be everything, all right, and and if things like that were a conflict we wouldn't have a quorum of any board in half the towns of Connecticut. All right so so those are not conflicts of interest they have come before the courts before.
The only thing I would ask I would ask each, member of the commission tonight to simply state that they will be reviewing this item,
from the perspective of a Planning and Zoning Commission member
and without regard to any other affiliations that you may have. I just everybody just go around and say yes I could do. If you can't do that then you do need to all avail yourself.
But I believe all of you can and I just want to hear you say it on the record that you'll be reviewing this as a planning and zoning commission member only.
>> Okay, well I'll start off by saying that I certainly will.
Ankerme?
Yes, same here.
>> Scott?
Didn't hear you, Scott. Yes.
Okay, thank you.
Steve Nelson?
Yes.
Leigh Ann Hutchinson?
Yes, I feel I'm able to do that. Okay. I'm also going to ask the alternates because
I don't know
it looks like we won't have to seat any of the alternates tonight, but
I don't know when we will actually act on the application and therefore
we'll understand that. Ann Blanchard?
Yes.
Kevin Arneson?
Yes, I will.
Susan England? Yes.
Okay. Thank you very much. Thank
>> you, Attorney Branch.
After we hear from Attorney Branch on the proposed changes,
we'll open up the
floor to the
Commission for any questions that they might have.
They'll have a chance to ask you throughout the public hearing here and then we'll go around and solicit input from the public.
If the Commissioner wants to ask a question
during
the public hearing,
we certainly can.
I don't want to close the hearing and find out like we did with the Dollar General
public hearing that we weren't able to ask the applicant any more questions after the public hearing was closed.
So I'll be very careful tonight to make sure that we're all satisfied with that we got the information
we need before we go ahead and
decide whether to continue or close the public hearing.
Based
on the number of people,
screen shows that we've got 37 people here tonight.
I would ask that you limit your comments to about three minutes.
Anne Cremay will be our timekeeper tonight.
And
if once we go around, if somebody feels they didn't have enough time to
make their case, we'll go back for round two until we make sure that everybody's had a chance
to
say what they need to say tonight.
So,
that,
Carol Ann, do you need to allow me to share my screen?
And you're muted, Carol Ann.
>> Yes, I took
that off. I
do not know
if I need you to share. Do I need to press share for you?
Well, it says host disabled participants
Multiple participants can share simultaneously?
Yes click that. Thank you.
>> Mr. Chairman just one question for Mark Ridge the record. Is Mr. Anderson going to present the text amendments
or who?
>> I was going to do that. You're just gonna review them? Yes. Okay.
>> Attorney Brandt sets perp this is Eric Anderson. That's perfectly acceptable with the town.
>> Okay.
So
everybody should be able to see section five of the Andover Rural Design District.
And as we're going down in the first, you know, the first group
of items here, it says the following uses are permitted
subject to the stated requirements.
And if we go down to 5.04,
it had public parks, playgrounds, and athletic fields.
We moved that into the special permit category based on the thought that
some
of the lots
in the ARD
residential district,
there might be, you might not want to put a ball field or a playground or a park there.
So, gives us a chance to get input and consider input from the public as opposed to having that as a matter of right. So,
that's why we crossed that out there and we'll include that down below.
Again, this was the draft that I put out to everybody early on, so we'll be discussing this when we got down to the special permit uses.
We
crossed the word schools out and put municipal land uses in.
We were considering that the school
would be a municipal land use.
And so
that's why we did that.
A couple other housekeeping items that that we were going to take care of as we went through.
The
5A2,
we were going to change the word churches to houses of worship.
Every church is a house of worship, but not every house of worship is a church.
And so we thought we would make that just a little bit cleaner.
Took libraries out of that line because that would be included in the municipal land uses
category.
So that's the point of that
change there.
Down in
5A
0.11,
we were going to replace private recreation areas
with the public parks, playgrounds and athletic fields. These are the same words that were as of right before,
but we put it in the special permit category so that we could have a public hearing and get input from the public on that.
One change that I would like to revert back to is we were going to cross out private recreational areas
because,
you know, we thought that that was included within the public parks, playgrounds, athletic fields.
As I was thinking about this, I recognized
that out on Route 316,
Andover has an archery range.
And I thought that probably fit the description better of private recreational area
better than park, playground, and athletic field.
And I thought that was perfectly
acceptable by special permit to have that.
So instead of in the proposal where I show that we cross that out,
I would retain that and then you'll renumber public parks, playgrounds, athletic fields
in beds and breakfast establishments
down there.
So those
are
the proposed changes at this point to
Section five.
This is the Section 24, the definition section.
And
originally, when we were
taking, you know,
working with the town on their request for a modification,
I was gonna
include a couple of
old action items that I had had that I was trying to get done.
One of those was to put in the definition of lot frontage.
I do not want to include that in the discussion any longer. I don't think that met the intent of what our
posting for a public hearing was. And so I think that definition is inappropriate.
And so I will take that out.
We did include
a
definition of municipal land uses,
building structures,
and uses of the town of Andover or any regional public agency
of which it is a member, but not including
public uses by other agencies or entities.
And so you have to ask yourself what is a public use?
And so we compared
that, we put in a definition for that.
Down here, it talks about the public being a building structure uses which are open to the public and owned by or under the exclusion
or the control of nonprofit charitable or social entities
compared to municipal land uses.
So that gives you the other uses,
not necessarily owned by the public, but they could be,
but they're not the municipal land uses. So that was covering all those other things. And I did think,
you know, again, we talked about the archery range.
We had in here the previously existing
definition of private recreational area.
And I think that does fit the bill for the archery range. And so I wanted to
include that.
I think that was it for the definitions.
That was it for the change.
And so,
at this point,
I'd ask
Eric Anderson
from the town if he's got any additional comments that he would like to make at this point.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Mr. Chairman and members of the Andover Planning and Zoning Commission, thank you for allowing me to speak.
As you know, the Planning and Zoning Commission is empowered by state law and the town of Andover Charter to act as a combined planning commission as well as a zoning commission.
The commission acts with the legislative authority when it writes regulations and creates land use law for the town of Andover.
As the former chairman of that commission,
I appreciate your efforts in reviewing what is before you tonight.
The town of Andover applied
to the Planning and Zoning Commission
to change the regulations in the Andover Rural Design District.
This is the town's primary,
but not only residential district.
Although most of Andover's buildings and properties are located in this district,
our current zoning regulations
do not allow for buildings or uses in this zoning district.
The town seeks to change this.
Put very simply,
our goal
is to allow municipal uses
via special permit in the Andover rural design.
That's it.
This means that when the town wants to construct something in the residential district,
it would submit a special permit application to the Commission.
The Commission then reviews and determines compliance with regulations
through its executive powers.
The Planning and Zoning Commission is required to hold a public hearing on the application so that everybody can have their opinions heard.
By requiring a special permit,
the Commission retains the full executive authority to rule on applications.
This is how the system is supposed to work.
In submitting this proposal for a zone change,
I propose the simplest change
that would accomplish the town's goal.
Like all other zone changes, the town zoning attorney,
attorney Mark Brantz
reviews
the documentation.
Attorney Brantz then recommended some additional changes to be made concurrently.
In no way is the town trying to change the way the regulations of of the town of Andover treat the Andover Elementary School or the Andover Board of Education
or transfer
authority from one entity
to another.
An awful lot of people have misconstrued
this somehow
as diminishing the authority of the school board or making schools somehow illegal.
That was neither the intent
nor what the proposal would do.
Subsequent to that, the Board of Education hired their own zoning attorney to review the proposed change,
and then the zoning attorneys for the town and Board of Ed discussed
those changes.
And I'm happy to support the changes
that were recommended by the Board of Education's
attorney.
That's it, and I thank you for your time and consideration.
Okay. Thank you, Eric.
>> Agent Halsey, do you have anything for us at this point? I just want to note that state statutes require that municipalities refer
both zoning regulations
amendments
to both
regional planning agency
or their council
governments in this case and abiding towns. Just want the record to note that this has been done. No comments have been received.
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you, agent Halsey.
Attorney Branch.
>> And unmute.
Yeah that that I the only thing I would say is, in reviewing attorney Williams' letter,
I thought that if we if the commission wishes to include the language that he suggested we should probably say
including but not limited to the board of education and the only reason I say that is sometimes
library boards ambulance societies fire companies
Sometimes they're quasi municipal
so that way if you have any of those
sort of mixed municipal public private partnerships,
they'll be included.
Otherwise,
I
think that's a perfectly fine change
I think the board of it is an agency of the town of Andover, but if it makes people feel more comfortable to have that called out specifically
we could certainly do that.
>> Okay,
thank you attorney branch.
Do any of the Planning and Zoning Commission members have any
comments
at this point or questions?
Nope.
>> I
made a statement last time at the last meeting that I feel like we need to leave the school as one of the
special permit
possibilities,
you know, instead of changing it completely to municipal, but have municipal
there. We need that and also have school listed.
>> Mr. Chairman, for the record Mark Brades, I heard that point last time and I I I think I misunderstood it but I still think it's valid.
One of the things we realized was that if we take schools out completely
we may have prohibited
private schools, which I don't think was the intent at all.
One of the things that the commission can do is simply retain
the category of school,
but just have it be private
schools, because that is a separate category that would not be included under municipal land uses.
>> Okay,
so if I were to follow what you were just saying, Attorney Branch,
we
would have the category schools in there, but they would not
pertain to Andover Elementary School, it would only pertain to private schools, or it would pertain to both?
And you're muted again.
>> It would be I would suggest that it just be private because otherwise it would be duplicative.
If we're including Board of Ed as a municipal as a municipal agency and municipal land use that includes public schools
so then we'd be duplicating.
But if we say if for schools it just says we take out the word public it would just be private and make it private schools.
Yeah. And I have some text to do that if that's what the Commission wishes to do.
>> Okay and and just you know as
we've alluded to a letter from the Board of Ed's
land use attorney
that gave us some
modification
suggestion
to the
definition of municipal land use.
If
in line with what attorney branch was saying, if we took
the Andover elementary school and listed it as a
school outside of the municipal land use,
then we could not
include
attorney Williams, I think it was for the board of education's comment. That's correct.
That way the school would not be land
use. Correct.
>> And so that is one of the things we'll have to discuss
during our deliberation
tonight.
Any
other commission members want to speak at this point?
>> Hi, this is Leanne. I have a question. Go ahead, Leanne.
Yes,
for Eric,
I think near the end of his remarks,
think he said that he
was in agreement with other suggestions
or any suggestions, and that I'm just looking for clarification made by the Board of Ed. So, it was my understanding that
the only thing we were really acting on tonight is to leave the word school
or private school
in.
So I'm just asking for clarification
from Eric if he's representing that we're going to include anything else as far as suggestions that were made by the Board of Ed or their attorney.
>> So,
it's obviously the Commission's
prerogative
on
what exact language
that the Commission chooses to use
from the town's perspective,
as long as municipal
uses
are permitted by special permit in the Andover Rural Design District,
The town is
happy.
>> Okay,
thank you. I guess that answers my question. Then I guess if anything else along these lines comes up during
further discussion,
then we'll go from there. Thank you.
>> Okay.
So, any
other comments or questions from the Commission?
Okay. Then we'll move into
the public comment portion.
And again,
please try to keep your comments to
under three minutes.
But I would like to start with the Chairman of the Board of Education,
Jerry Cremay, if I could. Do you have any comments for us, Jerry?
>> Thank you for this public hearing,
Chairman Larson.
I'm going to defer to Doctor. Chris Barnard, our Vice Chair,
because at a board event meeting, we nominated him to be our spokesperson.
So I would like to
defer to Doctor. Bernard.
>> Okay.
There And he is. Okay. In that case,
Chris Bernard,
I'll invite you to make any comments to the commission
that you would like to. Thank you very much. I did get your letter and
read it, understand it, and passed it on to the other Commission members
to read for tonight as well.
>> Thank you very much. And so Chris Barnard,
I'm Vice Chair of Board of Education, as Jerry said, and I am here to speak on behalf of the entire Board of Education. So that should hopefully limit some of the comments on
making us able to get out earlier.
We are certainly in support of the changes recommended by the town. We do feel very strongly across the unanimously across the entire board that we would like to see the term schools
left in planning and zoning commission,
or left in the planning and zoning guidelines. We feel it's important that schools are called out separately.
Well, Andover doesn't typically have to deal with that currently.
You know, we don't know in one hundred years what Andover will look like, and one of the reasons why
zoning laws call schools out specifically
is because oftentimes we have some very special regulations
that apply to what can go near a school within certain speed distance of schools and maintaining that is important in our mind to protect the safety of the children
and ensure their proper education.
And so we would support that keeping schools.
If Planning and Zoning Commission does not want to keep schools in there, then we also support the changes
recommended by the lawyers
and making sure that we're covered there. But we do feel that keeping schools in there makes us as clean as possible and in alignment with many other towns across Connecticut and across The United States.
That's all I have. Thank you. Okay,
>> and certainly,
you know, in
your letter, and
alluded to at our last meeting by
Anne Cremay,
I will say that I was not aware of the
responsibility,
authority,
jurisdiction,
if you will,
of the
Board of Education
with respect
to the school property.
So I
still struggle a little bit, and that will be for part of our deliberation
further on,
is how can we not
consider the school a municipal building? And I know there were considerations such as,
you know, not everybody can enter into
the school, but I think there are probably
other municipal buildings like courthouses and that, that
the general public does not have
the ability to go in as well. And so,
a concern
might be that if we break the schools out separately from the municipal building,
is there or would someone else want maybe the library broken out onto their own and that sort of thing? And I think
I
consider the Board of Education to be part of the town of Andover.
And as Eric
mentioned
earlier,
we certainly
did not and cannot
take any of the authority away from the Board of Education.
It's just, you know, my
question is wrestling with this from a zoning perspective,
which is essentially saying,
can we build a school or a town hall
or a firehouse or a community center in the Andover Rural Design District?
Those are all the same.
Why school got put in there originally and none of those other buildings that we built?
I don't have any idea.
But, you know, in my heart, I still consider
the school to be a municipal building.
But I am certainly willing to work collaboratively
to try and reach
agreement
that
satisfies,
the Board of Education
as long as we're not violating
a law
by doing so.
>> Mark
Richard Mark Rayds, mister chairman, that's why I was thinking of including but not limited to Board of Ed because you're right. You might have, you know, do we have to list the library board with the fire commission? But I think including but not limited to
calls out the Board of Ed for its special role and and yet recognize that there may be other agencies.
When you,
when, when you have a special permit use, they're reviewed individually.
For example, a municipal garage
is not open to the public and is a very different use from a municipal library,
which is a very different use from a municipal
fire fire department fire firehouse.
So municipal uses can be very different in the character of their traffic, the volume of visitation,
the amount of parking that they need, the locations that are suitable for them,
and special permits. Each of those uses can be evaluated
separately
for whether they are suitable in that location as designed and as proposed.
So,
I think if you include that that's fine and I'm not sure if I quite understood Doctor. Bernard but I think,
we
certainly don't mean to exclude private schools or dance studios or karate schools and that certainly can can remain included.
But I think that I think that seems to resolve the issue I think. Thank you.
>> So I stand educated on the Board of Ed's responsibilities
and authorities and I certainly want to make sure that
we recognize those special
authorities
that the Board of Ed has.
At this point, I'd like to call on
our school superintendent,
Valerie Bruno,
if you have any comments to make tonight.
>> Thank you, Jed.
I know that doctor Bernard is speaking on behalf of the Board of Education.
On behalf of the administration of the school, I would just like to add,
we are in complete agreements. The
letter that was written by the attorney Joe Williams of shipment and goodwin.
Did say in his opinion that it would be appropriate to maintain reference to school and the proposed definition.
And so I would reiterate that we also would ask
of this planning and zoning commission to please keep the word schools in there. Is definitely a lot of laws that pertain to schools. There's a school law book solely
to educate us on some of the differences.
And so I would just ask that they keep the reference, maintain the reference that's currently in there. Thank you.
>> So would you be satisfied?
I'm sure you have lots of rules.
You be satisfied
if we did
the modification
that Attorney Williams
suggested
is tweaked just a little bit by attorney branch to
recognize
the board of education in the municipal land uses.
Well, not have public school
called out by itself. Would that be an acceptable solution?
>> Well, again, the attorney made two recommendations
in that letter. The first was that it would be his opinion to leave school in there. But the other recommendation
was that if that was not the case,
I know Eric had, and thank you Eric, Eric had said he was not opposed to adding Andover Board of Education, but in the letter the recommendation
states that
he would define municipal
land uses as building structures and using uses of the town of Andover
Andover Board of Education and any regional public agency for which its member, including schools,
but not including public uses by other agencies. So if both of those
sets of wording were in there that were recommended,
I understand that that would be acceptable as well.
But I just wonder if it's just easier to to keep the word schools and maintain that in there as the attorney recommended. So, again, that's up to the planning and zoning, but thank you. Thank you for allowing me to make my comment.
>> Attorney Branch, I did not recall in attorney Williams letter
>> that he wanted to keep the schools broken out as separate. He did not. No, that was not in his letter. What he did say was he wanted to have the word including schools
in the municipal end use, and I would just say including public schools or including
town schools,
and that's fine. And then we just keep schools but that's private. So you have a category for municipal schools and you have a category for municipal for non municipal schools.
And that should that should solve it. So then you can allow public schools and private schools.
But he he definitely he definitely was including schools
under municipal land uses.
That was clearly his intent,
and I I don't have any problem with that.
Superintendent
Bruno,
>> do do you have a copy of the letter in front of you so we can Yep. Do. And I know Eric had posted it. It says, I understand it. I'll just read it for everybody who doesn't have it in front of them very quickly, and I'll stay under three minutes.
I understand the intent of the amendment in broadening the special permit use allowed in the ARD and making it consistent with other sections of the regulations.
However,
it is my opinion that it would be more appropriate to maintain reference to school use in the proposed definition of municipal land uses in section 24.
Schools are unique use in that, in my experience, they're specifically listed
when they're permitted in a particular zoning district. The proposed definition of municipal land uses also lists buildings and uses of the town and the regional public agency,
but omits reference to the Landover Board of Education.
By removing reference to school both school and the board, proposed amendment could be construed as intending to make schools a nonconforming
use in the ARD,
which I'm sure is not the intent.
Under the language as proposed, the Andover Elementary School would then be rendered nonconforming
as it is not operated by the town or by a regional public agency. To remedy this,
on behalf of the board, I propose the following
minor tweak to the pending proposal to amend 24.3
definitions,
municipal land uses, buildings,
structures,
and uses of the town of Andover,
Andover Board of Education,
or any regional public agency of which it is a member including schools
but not including public uses by other agencies or entities entities compared compared to to public. Public.
>> And and I think that that's what I was saying was just to including public schools.
And I think because you're right. But he was definitely calling for it in this definition.
He wasn't calling for it as a separate definition.
He wasn't calling for a separate term. He was calling for it to be in here, and I think that's fine. So,
>> well,
I'm still not
sure we're on the same page. One of my goals tonight was to make this a very boring
meeting.
And so,
it looks like that will
be the case.
And I did get the letter out
in going back
in,
superintendent,
you read this sentence here and here's where I have my question.
However, in my opinion, it would be more appropriate to maintain reference to school
use in the proposed definition
of municipal land uses in Section 24.
So,
did not read that letter as a recommendation
to
maintain schools as a separate line item in Section five
of the special permit categories.
That was clearly not his request.
So,
>> and again, I
I will
Right. I'm trying to use the Covey principle. I am seeking to understand before being understood. And that's why I am not trying to be confrontational
or
anything. I'm just trying to make sure that I understand what
the Board of Ed's attorney proposed
to us. And
so
I do
I take it that the Board of Ed would prefer
to have
Section five with municipal land uses
and schools separately.
And then with Attorney Williams
recommendation, at least the way I read it, to include
schools
separately
to recognize that authority
in the definition of municipal land uses. And so when when we get the deliberation
at least I understand the differences
and I will work hard
to.
To see if.
I think we'd all like to have, I'm looking for that win win solution.
And so we'll work hard to see where we can go there.
But
at least the way I read Attorney Williams letter,
he did not, he was not asking to maintain schools as a separate line in paragraph five.
>> Right. Or on the bottom under municipal uses, there were just those two highlighted ones,
both handover board of education
including schools.
And absolutely,
I see Mark shaking his head attorney Mark. Yep, that's absolutely
acceptable as long as both of those are in there.
And thank you. Okay.
>> Thank you.
One of the things, whenever we've held a public hearing,
I
have always learned more than I thought I was going to. And
hopefully,
that'll continue here.
I'm going to just go through the
names as I see them on the screen and I'm going to run out of screen before we run out of participants.
So I'll probably
ask Carol Ann to give me some help.
The bottom names on here, but I'm going to
Jordan Knight, do you have any comments for us?
No.
Okay, thank you. Jesse
Courier.
Oh,
in again
Carol Ann, I see most people have both first and last name
listed on here. I think that's given you what you need for
your records.
Thank you. Head to the next speaker is going to be Louise and and we'll need to make sure we get her last name on there. Okay, so Jesse Courier back to you.
>> Thank you. I'm in support of keeping schools
and
the suggestion of including the board of Ed. Thank you.
Okay.
Louise.
>> Hi. I do have a question.
I'd like to know if changing the wording
will affect the future use of the school for any type of community purposes, so like public hearings and emergency shelters?
>> Changing the No,
it would
not.
In fact, it actually makes it easier to do those things.
Okay.
Thank you.
This
is Louise Goodman.
Goodwin.
Goodwin. Okay.
Thank you.
Julia Haveralla.
>> I am in favor of following the
recommendations
of the Board of Ed
legal counsel
and
keeping the word schools and
Board of Education
in there,
in the regulations.
>> Is it is that in the definition, Julia? Or is that in the section five
separate from municipal buildings,
municipal land uses?
Section five.
>> Okay.
Thank you.
Next person up is a phone number ending in 3334.
Okay, I'm going to move on.
Bob Hamburger, any comments?
>> Yeah, I'm also in favor of following what the attorneys do.
I'm not going to second guess
what these folks, even though
everybody knows I was once chair of planning and zoning and had a fair amount of training
in land use
laws and terminology,
defer to the experts, the people with the letters after their name.
Now,
it came up in discussion,
this maybe could be something that you add to another agenda at some other time. But I think that the definition for private recreational areas that we have in glossary
or appendix
is
very poor.
It specifically
misses
the crucial aspect of a private recreation area, which is that it's privately owned.
Private recreation area is a very commonly used land use term and privately owned is the most important part of it. But we have verbiage in there about nonprofit
organizations,
which is essentially irrelevant because a private recreational area
can be for profit or not for profit. I think the biggest example in our town is Andover Lake
is a private recreational area. It's something that's privately owned
and managed by an organization.
It requires residents
and or
paying a fee to access.
So, there are commonly available definitions that we could find and I think whether it's part of this meeting or another one that needs to be addressed because
there was a lot of discussion over the weekend
on a Facebook thread where Eric
had
made the announcement
for this meeting. And one of the things that came out of there was that people thought that the school playground was a private recreational area and it's not at all. So this is something that needs to be addressed.
That's all I've got to say. Okay, thanks Bob.
>> Would like to,
you said you agreed with the attorneys.
As we've seen, we've had two different readings of the attorney's letter. So
are you in favor of the reading that keeps in section five
municipal land uses
separate items, schools,
or
just municipal land uses with the definition to include schools.
>> Quite frankly, I have no opinion one way or the other, because as far as I can tell they are functionally the same.
Okay,
thank you.
Mary Hoeller.
>> Sorry, I just joined. I'm just catching up. No comment. Thank you. Okay.
Catherine
Magdalene
Lewis.
>> Hi,
Jen. It's Baldy Lewis. That's fine. Okay. Yep. Well,
>> and I knew you didn't have enough letters on there to give Carol Ann a chance of getting it into record. What? It's, yeah, it's way too long a name.
>> I just have one quick question, please, and then I'll offer it.
What
is negative
if you keep the word school in there? How is that perceived negatively? What does that do that
you would need to take the word out?
Put school in where?
>> In
section five or in where it has BOE. I guess if you're
taking it out, you're actually listing out municipal
and then the word school,
why
how was it a deterrent to take the word school out?
>> I guess I'm what I'm at this is for Mark Branch for the record.
We're getting confused about where school is.
Attorney
Williams has requested on behalf of the Board of Ed that the term including schools
be put under municipal land uses,
which no one seems to be objecting to.
The question was, we're going to eliminate schools
as a separate list, but didn't realize that would preclude private schools, dance schools, what parochial schools, whatever. So the idea that I'm hearing now is to keep schools
Skip, you want one class of schools is public schools of the town of Andorra
and also any other kind of school but to leave them both but one is public one is town
one is non town
is that what you were asking
I'm pretty sure that yeah I I think you clarified it for me thank you very much And Mr. Chairman before you close the hearing I've been playing with the language on my screen if you want at some point I can share my screen and show you what I'm getting out of the discussion but let's first see what other people have to say. Okay and
>> before we continue,
as a point of information,
in our section 24,
we have a definition
of school
college.
And that definition reads a college,
public school, or private school giving regular instruction
at least five days a week for eight or more months in a year. And I know, Attorney Branch, you had made
a comment that maybe we would eliminate the
five days a week, eight or more months a year,
but it would seem if,
maybe it would seem as if we left the word schools in there by itself,
that would cover both the public schools and private schools.
And then we would not need to include
anything about the schools and the municipal
>> land use. No, I think that
clouds it and I think that creates confusion.
Would just, what I was suggesting was that in the definition of school we have just take out public school.
So college or private school, whether you take out the five days a week is is a different topic. I mean a dance school for example might not have five days a week.
All right, it might have less and who cares?
I don't know but
but I was gonna have it say a college or private school giving regular instruction at least five days a week or eight or more months a year in the year not including municipal land uses. So we have private schools and we have town schools, and they're both listed as special permit uses.
And the board of ed is expressly listed under municipal
as requested by attorney Williams,
and schools is put back in requested by Attorney Williams. I think that's where everybody seems to be coalescing around. Yes.
>> All this different shit. Okay.
Thank you, Katherine. Kelly Hagerty.
Kelly, if you're trying to comment, you're on mute.
Okay, we'll come back at the end and give her another chance.
Johanna Dabari.
No comment. Okay,
thank you.
Celeste Willard.
>> Thank
you, Jed. On behalf of the Board of Ed,
I'm a member of the Board of Ed and I would just echo
what Doctor. Bernard has said as well as Superintendent
Bruno. Thank you.
>> Okay.
Caitlin McIntosh.
Kathy or Mike Palazzi?
And Mike Palazzi, you can both talk.
>> We're we're both here. Right? We've been having a big discussion about this.
We personally
well, I'll speak and then Mike can speak.
Personally feel that I do like the idea that it's we're one,
which is, like, municipal to me. It means everybody. We're we're one town. We're one but but my problem is I don't want the school neglected in any manner. I don't wanna leave it out in any manner. So with that, I have to agree
with the attorney
and and Chris Bernard
that he by the way, thank you. That was a very nice speech.
And
that's what I'm gonna say that because
I love the school, and I love my town, and I just
I want everyone to be happy and be a unit.
So that's my comment.
Mike?
Well,
>> I think I'm gonna go along with the
with my wife on this, and
I like what I'm hearing.
I don't see a great big difference I know. Between any of it, to be the truth. But as long as the school doesn't get hurt in what we're doing Right. I'm fine.
Okay?
No.
I'm talking about the language of its own.
Aaron Borys.
>> Don't know how to use this. Don't know if I'm Hey, there. I would just echo that I'm in support of the Board of Ed's attorney's letter in regard to utilization of school and Board of Ed being included.
I also just had one question. Changing this language or leaving the same, does that impact
where the placement of a community center would go in proximity to a school and school boundaries and such? If we're changing language, does that change something in relation to where this building would be built? If it's all municipal, does it make it easier?
>> Makes no difference at all.
Each each each for the record Mark Brands each
each special permit use
each municipal land use would be a separate application
so it doesn't make it easier or harder.
Thank you.
>> I have
the name Jesse
and I don't know if that's that looks like it's spelled different than Jesse Courier so if you're a different person, now is a good time to speak, and we need your last name.
Okay, I'm going to move on.
Jesse Courier, we gave you an opportunity to speak, did we not?
>> Yes, you did. Okay, thank you. Jessie was not me. JoAnn Herbert?
>> I
basically am here to listen.
I echo a couple people
saying that I would hope that we're just one town. We're so small and that everyone would have the best interests of the school at heart with making any decisions
as well as any decisions for the town in general. But again, I'm here to listen.
I don't see a lot of difference between a couple things and
thank you.
Catherine Hutchinson.
I have no comments or questions.
You. Thank you.
Kimberly Persson.
No comments right now. Thank you. Mike
>> Beckwith?
Yes, as a fellow Board of Education member, I'm just here to echo the comments made by Doctor. Bernard and the Superintendent Bruno. Thank you.
Paula King.
Hi, Jed. No comment. Thank you very much.
Shannon Louden.
>> Thanks, Chairman Larsen, thank you very much for holding this public hearing and public comment.
And it's loud and as anybody else who's on here who knows me knows that it would be.
That's just because I'm loud, Jed. As
a member of the Board of Education,
I certainly defer to the comments of Doctor. Bernard and Doctor. Bruno or almost Doctor. Bruno,
our superintendent.
And as an attorney, I very much appreciate
the involvement
and the cooperation of attorney Brantz and the attorneys for the Andover Board of Education.
Thank you.
>> Mr. Chairman for the record Mark Brantz just one thing I want to say in response to Ms. Loudon.
Attorney Williams and I go back a long time and he's he is really fantastic,
and he and I always always work things out.
Glad to hear it. Thank you very much.
I see Jeff Murray.
>> Hi, Jed. I'm just here to listen to the comments and then get a little education as you said too. So
no comment. Thanks. Okay.
>> And that is all the names that I see. Is there somebody that I missed as we were going through?
Okay, I'm going to circle back
to Chris Bernard,
and
you listened
to all this input.
I still
am thinking that there is a disconnect between what you want
and
what
Attorney Branch
is thinking that you're
in agreement with.
>> Well, Mr. Chairman, how about if I show you what I've got on screen and then everybody can see it. Okay.
All right. I'm going see if I can share screen here and get to the right screen.
Wait a minute.
Okay.
One moment.
All right, share screen.
See if yes this should be it.
Okay are you able to see
are you able to see what I have here for municipal land uses now? Yes.
Okay so what I'm going read it and the bold
is what's different
from what we advertised.
Okay so I mean it's building
structures and use of the town of Andover and I was going to put
including
oops sorry wait a minute
but not limited to
to
the Andover Board of Education
or any regional public agency which is a member including public schools
but not including public public uses by other agencies or entities. For example,
a dance school open to the public or a karate school open to the public that's not a municipal land use.
So I'm before I leave that any questions on what's up there now.
Okay, and then I was going to put under school leaving that definite they were in definitions now
school a college or private school
giving regular instruction at least five days a week for eight or more months in the year, not including municipal land uses. So this is again this is the parochial school or the dance studio or whatever.
Right.
And then for
the, let me get the other section five.
So five would say
it would have municipal land uses,
the houses of worship we talked about,
we would keep parks playgrounds and athletics fields that's there now, but instead of permitted it would be special permit,
then schools colleges,
so again that's private schools and then putting back in private recreational
areas,
sticking the reference there to something by, Andover Lake Association
or the Archery Range or things of that kind.
So that's what I've got from this and I'll
leave this on screen until anyone wants me to take it off
or see it again.
>> Go
ahead and take it off at this point,
attorney branch.
Okay.
There
>> you go. So, I still
have a concern
that
the Board of Education
feels
that
we should leave schools
is aligned under municipal land uses, but that school
is
not
necessarily a private school, it is the public school,
that it's separate from a municipal land use.
>> Well the way I have it is it's it's just it's just what Jerry Williams asked for it's it so it's
a municipal land use is any municipal land use including
municipal
of board of ed including specifically schools. I could put schools libraries firehouses blah blah blah I could do all of that but
I for some reason there's a preference to list schools separately
I don't have an issue with that.
>> Think the school that you're must be, well, go ahead, Chris. I was gonna say, and just clarify from the Board of Education's perspective.
I think the reason why we originally approached this was saying we'd like to keep the 5A.
Definition of schools areas.
Well,
we're one of the conforming uses currently per zoning code. We're the correct ones.
So if it's not broke, why fix it? First of all,
think it like I said, I think it also makes it clear. That said,
if we decide
not to leave that there,
the Board of Education is also supportive of the language that the
lawyers have put together.
So if we want to remove the one, we are certainly happy with the language that has been assembled.
>> Okay,
and I think it was Bob Hamburger who,
I went back and pressed him on which of those two
options you want,
said they sound about the same to me.
That's kind of
where I
am at at this point. I think it does
significantly
recognize,
no matter which way we go,
we have made significant improvement in recognizing the responsibility,
authority, and jurisdiction of the Board of Education
in
the zoning regulations of all places
there. Eric, did you have a comment?
>> I just I actually have one comment for one question for attorney grants,
and that is right now this only affects the Andover Rural Design District.
We do have another residential
district, which is the Andover Lake District.
As far as I know, the town does not own any municipal property
in the Andover Lake District, which is why I did not include this in the zoning.
But what the town does have is the town has a series
of
structures
so that the fire department can withdraw water.
Would that? Oh. We we have never in the past applied to zoning when we added those.
Is that something that should have been included,
and should this be broadened to the Andover Lake zone also
to address those concerns,
whether we do it at this meeting or at another?
>> For the record, Mark Brains,
there's no harm in adding municipal land uses to the Andover Lake zone. However, I'm familiar with the the the the the structures you're describing,
And those would be a pertinent considered a pertinent to the streets.
I mean, we don't have to list streets as a permitted use.
So anything to pertinent to them. And, and as you probably know those those structures are also exempt from wetlands.
So yeah, it's in
the long term. I mean, regulations have needed a major overhaul
were
since you hired me in 1981.
And,
so,
yeah, those are the kinds of things that we've missed.
And,
but I,
I do so yes, it's I mean, you may at some point want
a fire substation or a
school bus waiting
a building in the Andover Lake zone and currently municipal land uses are permitted in that zone and they should be. So yes that's that's that should be on our to do list.
Okay, thank you. That's all I have, Jed. Okay,
>> thanks, Eric. I
am going to go back
to ask the Commission one more time.
If now that we've heard from everybody from the public,
if there are any other questions or comments from the Commission members.
Okay. I have
>> none, Chad. Yeah.
Hearing
none,
we get to the point where we will make a decision on continuing
or closing the public hearing.
And
I guess I
think I understand
the issues. I think we're
close with a couple of tweaks that might make some folks
happier or
I think we could probably satisfy
everybody, might not be exactly
the way they want.
But
is there any commission member who thinks at this point we should not be closing the public hearing?
And hearing that, I will ask the Commission for a motion to close the public hearing.
>> I'll make a motion to close the public hearing, Jed. Thank you, Steve.
I'll second that.
That was Kevin?
Scott.
Scott. Okay.
>> That was Scott. Yeah.
Didn't see the little box right up. Thank you, Scott. Any
discussion?
And again, we haven't seated any commission members, so I will say all
in favor say aye.
Aye.
Any opposed?
Any abstaining?
Okay, the public hearing is closed.
Okay.
And we will move now to open
the regular
planning and zoning meeting.
So, is 08:09.
I will call the meeting to order.
Next up is roll call, seating of alternates.
I see President Ann Cremay,
Scott Persson,
Steve Nelson,
Leigh Ann Hutchinson,
and myself.
So that is the five regular commission members. Also present
are Anne Blanchard,
Kevin Arsenan,
and Susan England.
So none of the alternates will be seated for tonight's meeting.
Item three is addition or changes to the agenda and I would like to add an item
five
C under new business
to discuss the planet conservation and development submissions.
Are there any other changes
to the agenda?
Hearing none,
I'll make a motion to approve the change to the agenda to include the discussion
under new business, Planet Conservation and Development.
I'll second that. Thanks, Scott.
>> Any discussion?
Hearing none, all in favor say aye.
Aye.
Any
opposed?
Any abstaining?
The motion carries five-zero-zero.
Next item up is public speak.
Anybody didn't get their chance to speak at the public hearing who wants to on
anything?
Now's your chance. Anybody want to say something now?
I see Bob Hamburger wants to speak. Go ahead, Bob.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
At the public hearing I mentioned that there was a lot of online
chatter about the subjects that was discussed
on Facebook thread.
And I have to say it was encouraging and heartening to see so many people
that were interested in
land use issues.
And we know that these things can be
confusing, they can be complicated, they can be dry, but this was a fairly impassioned
set of discussions.
That was the positive side. The negative side was that there were a lot of people who had
a lot of misconceptions
about what the regulations
said, how to interpret these things. And I don't blame them. I mentioned when I was on P and Z, I had to do a lot of homework and
get a lot of formal training
and to his credit, Eric chimed in and said that anybody
who's not a member of the commission who
was really interested
and could demonstrate their interest by doing some of the online courses, Eric would then pony up the fee for the
in person all day long
land use for commissioners
or I forget the exact title of that,
that I went to a few years ago was extremely,
extremely valuable.
>> March 11.
Yes. March 11 all day, you should have the brochure by now. Well, I've been there so I don't need to.
What changes?
>> Yeah, so
I just want to point that out that
and I exhorted a couple of the people who were the most vocal there that if they're really concerned that the town is always looking for volunteers
that we are a small town with limited resources.
It was just my way of telling them to put up or shut up.
So
that's all I wanted to contribute at this point. Thank you for the floor.
>> Thank you, Bob. Any other public comment at this point?
Hearing none, we'll move on to new business.
And first item up is the proposed amendment to zoning regulations.
Amendments to section five and twenty four of the Andover zoning regulations so as to allow municipal land uses uses in the ARD zone and amend definition sections of the zoning regulation so as to clarify
intent.
Just
for the record,
now that we enter into deliberations
on the public hearing,
only those commission members that are actually seated can
discuss
the
item at this point. And so
that's where we are.
Mark Branch, you said
trying you
to keep up
with what you thought
the discussions
were
reflecting.
I guess I will let you put up
your first shot because
I think there's still,
as much as we tried to nail down what attorney Williams' letter
really said. I think there was some confusion in there.
And
I would just like I
want the commission to do the very best
job that we can tonight.
I'm gonna get Ankrami
take the first crack at what it should say, but since you said you were
keeping the text up to date, I'll let you
>> give it the first shot. Yep, Mr. Chairman, what I'm wondering is because there has been a lot of discussion here,
I'm wondering if you should
don't know if there's a deadline here, then maybe I would email you what I have on my screen. I I showed it to you and I can show it to you again of course, but I'm wondering if it might be better if I email it to you and at your next meeting you have it in front of you.
It's up to you.
>> I know
the I
know the
town was was hopeful that we would move this along just as quickly as possible.
>> I mean, I have it here. I can walk us through. I know you do and
>> I we've
got interested crowd here tonight to watch what we're doing.
>> All right I'll then I will share screen and I'll just walk you through what I've got. Okay.
Okay
and all right so
that's there we go.
All right well let me take this out a minute I'm all right you should be able to see my screen now. I can yep.
And I'm going to take that out just because I was I had this is what I call a working copy.
So
the blue
is what you advertised.
What I have now is what is in red.
Mhmm.
>> And by the way, warnings I just picked up on, I realized when we added Andover board,
right, or any regional publications of which it,
that makes it sound as if only the board and not the town, which isn't what you meant. So I put of which the town or the board is a member.
Right so the town could also like a dog kennel you may be regional dog kennel some towns are
health health district okay.
Now I have including but not limited to the annual Board of Education or any regional age of which the town or the board is a member
including public schools
but not including public uses by other agencies.
And I'm just gonna skip down to public.
So this is what you already advertised.
Public is defined here
is a non municipal use.
A religious school, a karate school,
a dance school,
anything of that kind.
And then after school college,
I just took out pub so a school college is a college or private school,
and now we exclude municipal land uses. So So we have two classes municipal land uses include public schools,
schools and colleges are private schools.
They're both
allowed in the zone we're getting there but they're separately defined
and what
I'm going to do for now just for these purposes I'm going to take that out because that's not what we're looking at anymore.
So this is what's on screen and then the other screen
is okay back up to this is section five
where
public parks playground athletic fields okay that is being moved
down to public as a special permit so it's still there it's just special permit
We add take out schools,
municipal land uses, so public schools, the house of worship we already talked about,
and then we add back in schools, colleges.
These are the private ones, and we add back in private recreation areas. So that's not really a change
because that was already there.
Private, they were already there.
I just and I I by the way, I could I could make this easier by putting public, but I you know what I can do? Hang on a second. I got an idea.
No it gets even simpler I hope.
Yeah and then we're gonna.
Best course I took in high school folks was typing.
All right so now you see what I've done now so we left in private recreation areas,
schools, colleges,
and then public parks, playgrounds those are public meaning
a non profit
so they remain allowed
in the zone by special permit. They're now permitted they end up a special permit and we administer land uses.
So anyone who wants to see any of that anywhere again it's your
call.
>> Okay,
I think everybody understands
what you've
displayed
on the screen.
So, at this point
What?
>> If
the Commission feels
that we should be discussing
this is
the change based on our discussion tonight,
We can make a motion. I'm looking for a motion to approve the
regulations
as just described
by Attorney Brantz.
>> I'll make a motion to adopt the language as
described by attorney Brantz. Okay.
Thank you, Steve. And
>> that has to say you have to pick an effective date
and the effective date must be no earlier
than the date that you can publish.
So I mean, I don't know. Jim, how long did it take you to do a legal notice of publication?
>> Get Get a a notice notice in
by the end of the week.
So you could say,
to be effective
February
>> February
or what do you just pick a date.
>> Are we not required to allow for the appeal period on that? No.
>> My mistake. No. In fact, no. No. Not at all. The effective date the effective date remains the same unchanged
but every every motion to amend the zoning regor text must include an effective date.
So if you say February 7, you're fine. Yes.
>> Okay so that date is
in the motion.
Carol Ann you've got the motion?
Yep
You're muted Carol Ann. You're muted. Steve
>> made the motion and did somebody second it? Scott Persson seconded the motion. And as seconded it was with the February 7 effective date? Yes.
>> Okay, so we've got a motion on the table that's been seconded.
Now
comes the fun part,
is
deliberation
on the motion
as
presented.
And
I think it was Catherine,
well, asked
the question,
what does it hurt
if
we put schools
separate from the municipal land uses
as a separate category and have it referred to
the
town of Andover Elementary School.
And
the only
thing I can,
in my answer is I'm not sure, so I'll give Attorney Branch the option to go after I get done.
But I heard Attorney Branch talk about it being duplicative because
the school building is a municipal building.
And so, to give it a separate category
in addition to that
might be wrong.
Certainly,
I
think
the intent
I
would
like to
to,
you know, there's a side of me that says,
if the school board wants
something that way
and it doesn't hurt us,
I'm ready to go there.
Eric Anderson mentioned his goal was to modify the regulations
such that
we could
build a community center
in the ARD.
The words that Attorney Branch
put up there
reached that goal
and reached what I think I heard from many of the public
speakers who certainly are
in favor
of
they like our school.
The downside is that then it gets a little muddy with respect to private school, public school. I don't know how to straighten that out exactly.
And there's the
legality
of having
a municipal
school
categorized
outside of that.
You know, if it's
all things being equal,
I would happily go with
what the Board of Education is
requesting because
we are not trying to
do anything untoward towards the Board of Education. And I want to make that
absolutely as clear
as I can.
My concern is that
is there anything
unwise
or
not legal
about
including
the public school in a separate category
from the municipal land users.
And Attorney Branch, I have to
go to you. I can read Attorney Williams' letter
both ways. I think he asked for a change to the definition
not to include the school section in there,
which is different than what I heard Ann Cremay talk to us about, what I heard Jerry Cremay talk to us about at the last Board of Education meeting
that I watched,
and
Chris Bernard
and the school superintendent
talked to us about tonight. So
all things being equal,
I think
I would like to
go with them. I'm just not sure
if that is the wisest route legally,
if there's something I don't know
that would get us in trouble by going that way.
>> The the way that we might get into trouble
is that we might have be talking about multiple principal uses
which is kind of a confusing area of the law.
If
if you group together,
you know, one of the questions you got during the public hearing was, you know, what if we use a school for a temporary shelter or a voting area or something like that? Okay.
And my response was that as it's drafted, that would not be an issue.
I would worry about having
a separate language category for school
and it gets approved as school. Does that mean then that you can't hold meetings in school?
That you can't have a blood drive in school?
Does that mean that you can't have, an emergency shelter in school because that's not a school?
So I think that by grouping them together,
you allow for those kinds of multi use things.
And, and I think by the way, that's why attorney Williams expressed his proposal the way that he did. I mean, he and I discussed it And I
think that that's the sensible way to do it.
>> Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you, Attorney Branch. I
had a thought and
it zipped right away. So maybe it'll come back later on.
Any other commission members
have any
thoughts on
the item here?
Let's see.
>> Ed, I think the language as proposed accomplishes
everything that the board of ed had brought up.
If we the only confusing area, I think, was section five,
whether schools was listed separately. And I think
as was pointed out, you you come up with a redundancy situation
at a minimum,
or
worst case, if schools are listed separate from
municipal buildings,
then the question is, why are they listed separate?
Are they not included in municipal buildings?
And I think that could be very confusing.
>> Okay.
Thank you, Steve.
I agree.
And it also
would require us to do something different
to continue
and maybe it would be just put private colleges and schools in that list of special permits.
The thought that I had that went in and out of my head
is that,
you know,
as
we discuss
things like blood drives,
voting
meetings
in the school.
The way I understand it is that is a Board of Education
decision whether or not to allow those as it is now.
And
certainly if the Board of Ed works
closely with the town,
I think they both recognize
what's best for the town
and
acts accordingly.
One of the things that
I know I still have confusion on,
and I was reluctant to bring this up tonight because it gets
away from the issue of just building a school
or building a community center in the ARD
is a discussion I heard at a board of selectmen meeting on
the January 9, I think it was. And the discussion was about
the
cool
school
summer program.
And what I heard was
the town felt they
should have some say
in that because the town provided
insurance coverage
and it is a town
building.
Based on what I heard recently
and that made sense to me when I heard that. Based on what I had heard recently before that, I would say, no, that
cool
summer program
camp
would have fallen under the Board of Education's
cognizance.
And
the comment that I heard was, you know, that the people that were running the program were talking to the Board of Education. They didn't recognize
that the town had something to say about that.
And so
I can I
agree that, you know, no matter which way we would go with the wording
in the zoning regs,
the question that
is probably out there is,
what
is the relationship
between the town
and the Board of Education, and I consider the Board of Education part of the town,
as Kathy and Mike Palazzo said, you know, we're all one?
What
expectations
does the town have
for the Board of Education making
decisions about the use of the school and the school property?
And what expectations does the Board of Ed have
that they should
work with the town
because the town has some say in that and I don't know what that is.
Anne?
Yeah. Go ahead, Anne.
>> The town
in a way
owns
the buildings,
but the board of education
has
by law control
over their buildings and that's their responsibility
to take care of the buildings.
So the town is like second when it comes to the buildings that the school is in.
The school is responsible
as long as there is a school with children in it until that school no longer functions as a school,
the school board has control of that building.
The town can come and ask, can we use this for this occasion?
And the school can say yes or no, as it's needed,
but
it's definitely
by.
>> Yeah, you're cutting out Ian, I don't know what happened, but
we're not hearing you.
>> School was getting their own insurance so the town doesn't have that anymore over them and
they're using the school building,
not the
town
building. They're not using
the town hall, they're using the school.
So
that was,
I know, I heard that meeting,
>> is way off
because it is the Board of Ed that's in charge of that. Okay.
>> And you say the Board of Ed is now responsible for the insurance over there at the school? I think COOL,
>> which is their own program,
has the insurance, if I'm correct.
Is that right, Valerie?
>> Jesse Courier is on and she's in charge of the finances
and the oversight of that program so she would be the best in luck Jeff Boyd has.
How does this relate
to the text amendment?
I guess He was thinking I don't
>> Okay. I withdraw my comment.
It's going to sneak back out to
the whole discussion on whether or not we
should close the public hearing.
And so we limited ourselves from the ability to have that discussion.
I guess we
are
where we are.
Okay.
Bad on my part. Should have kept my mouth shut.
Any other commission members?
We've heard from Anne, we've heard from Steve.
Leanne?
No, I I have no other comments. Okay, thank you, Leanne.
And
Scott Persson,
any comments from you?
No, I'm not set, Chuck. Thank you. Okay.
>> So I guess the
language that
Attorney Branch put up there for the proposal
certainly recognizes
the authority of the Board of Education.
I think it is consistent with what the Board of Education's
attorney,
Attorney Williams,
requested that we do.
And I understand
that it might be a little short
of what the Board of Education
and Ankremay
thinking should be there, as well as, you know, some
significant
portion of the members of the community that
weighed in.
Any other
questions from the Commission
before we vote?
And
again,
the vote is on the modified words
that Attorney Branch put
on the screen. Anybody want to see those again before we vote? Yes, yes, if we could, please. Okay.
>> Get those back up again.
It started to get unstable on screen so I closed it but I it's still there I could I could open it back up
Just one second sorry.
There we go.
Yeah so this is can you see it now?
Oh wait it failed to start.
All right wait a minute let's try it out. I don't know why.
Wait a minute I can see it on my screen.
I can see it on my screen.
It's
let's see something no it's not letting me do it now.
I can see it let me try something else let me see maybe I switch over.
Try again.
I'm gonna exit out and just try again.
Okay there we go let's see if that works.
Okay good there you go okay so here's here's municipal land uses this is the definitions section
and let me know when you want me to move on.
>> You are muted, Ann. So if you were asking to scroll down, we didn't hear it. No?
Okay why don't you go ahead and scroll down Mark. Okay and then there's public
>> that there's no changes to that from what you advertised
and then school
still kept as a separate definition but now it's a non public a non municipal school I should say not non public a non municipal school
So it could be a
satellite of Manchester Community College or
Prince Tech or something could be that.
So that's definitions.
Let me know if you want me to go to five.
Yep, go to section five.
Is there five ARD?
>> Again public parks play event just We still see
the definitions Mark.
You don't see Section five ARD?
No. Nope.
I'm going to try to refresh this then.
Now?
>> Yes. Now we do. Yep. Okay, all right. Good. I thought it would flip from the other screen. It does. It made me switch.
Okay,
so you see there's the Parks playground just moved down.
Municipal land uses the house of worship
and then so private recreation area stays so no change.
Schools colleges but now we're talking private
and we put back in public parks, playgrounds, and athletic fields now as a special permit use.
>> I still don't get why we'd take up
change that schools thing
to colleges. Why not still include public schools?
>> Because it's a municipal land use. There you have two overlapping definitions.
I can't see the problem with that, but
>> What are people applying for?
You you can't have you can't have definitions overlapping.
They've got to be distinct categories.
Okay.
>> Okay, I think you can close that out now,
Mark. Okay.
Any other questions or comments?
>> So,
then you're assuming that the school, Andover Elementary School is a municipal use.
Is that correct? Yes, correct.
>> Correct.
And I read that to be consistent with Attorney Williams letter. Yes. On the subject.
So, this point,
I'm going to call roll call vote.
Anne?
I
guess I'll say aye.
Scott? Aye.
Steve?
Aye.
Leigh Ann?
>> And I vote aye as well. The motion passes
500.
>> I will email that to
the zoning office now so you have that text.
>> Thank you everybody for your participation tonight on
that.
I know it's not exactly
what the Board of Education was looking for,
but I did hear that the Board of Education would be satisfied with that answer and
I hope that that is true.
Going on to
new business
item 5B,
the Connecticut Bar Association workshop for land use agencies,
Saturday, March 11. I
sent the agenda
for that out to the various commission members.
And
the thing that
you know we need to do is, you know, last year, last time it was held,
Agent Halsey submitted
on
my behalf anyhow the
attending.
I went to try and apply to attend
and it wants, you know, payment
at time of application.
And
the town I know is going to pay for that training.
And so
I'm thinking
that
Agent Halsey is going to have to
submit
an individual application for each of us,
but
he's going to need your
name, address,
and email
address so they can send you the big thick book that
gets put out worth its weight in goal for doing
land use business.
And then they need your email address because they'll email you the link
to join the zoom training session.
So
Jim's going to need to get that in by the February 15.
>> And by the way this as as was two years ago when it's over they will also email you the recording
of the all day
and during the day you can ask you can use the chat function
to ask questions.
Two years ago we answered about 150 questions
and anyone who participates will also get a list of all those questions and all the answers.
>> Yep, so everything you ever wanted to know about land use you get your chance to ask for free
and so
that's a good deal too. But let Jim know you know by
prior to the February 15 so he can get the
thing in there and that's before our next meeting. So that's why I wanted to talk about that tonight.
>> Jed, if I may, I would also say on the town's behalf, this is a fantastic
program.
And as you all know, you are now have a requirement
for a minimum amount of education
for a land use member?
And attorney Brandt could probably speak to this, but I suspect
this would
check that box completely in addition to be an absolutely fantastic training opportunity.
>> Unfortunately,
the the OPM published its requirements after we had set this agenda.
You have to have one hour
of affordable and fair housing.
This program only does a half an hour.
So yeah that little next time next time we'll fix that okay but
clear Connecticut land use education research
is also doing its advanced land use Those are going to be three Thursdays in February.
And the third one of those will be an hour and a half
on
fire housing and
fair housing and
housing opportunity.
So
that's clear if you just look if you have Connecticut labor's education
UConn clear it'll show up that's going to be in February it's like three successive Thursdays for an hour and a half each night and I'll be doing the affordable housing piece by the way but yeah everything else except that last half hour of affordable housing will be met by by the March 11.
>> Okay
so we're going to move on at this point to five
C, the plan of conservation and development.
Last
Wednesday
was
the due date for any
bids to be submitted
for assisting us with the development of the plan of conservation development.
We got two. I sent the link out
to all the Commission members so you should have that.
The question is,
and we have been granted
authority, if you will, by the Board of Selectmen to be the deciding body for which one gets selected to assist us with that.
So, you know, the next
comment is, so how do we
do that?
You know, talking over with Eric,
it seems like it would be good to have
each of the firms that submitted a proposal
come talk to us so we can ask them questions, get to know them a little bit. We did that with the
town engineer
solicitation.
I thought that went very well. And there's only two, so it won't take very long. But
I thought both the applications were very good.
One came in at like $52,000
The other one came in at $70,000
But,
you know, we really want to get the
team that's going to do the best for the town. And
Eric said he would go out and negotiate,
or at least attempt to negotiate a better price if we picked the more expensive guy.
The other comment I have on
them at this point, and I thought they both had good write ups,
they
indicated they would be complete quicker than I thought. So,
one guy said he would be done in a year, the other guy, you know, fifteen months.
But
one of my goals for planet conservation and development
is that the date on it is in 2025.
You know, we're only required to do this every ten years. I want to get our full ten years money's worth out of the last one before we reset the clock.
And so,
will be part of the discussion is
making sure that it ends up
with at least January 2025 on the cover page so that we get another full ten years of credit.
Anybody got any thoughts on that being the right approach to
is the next step to help us select?
And I guess, you know, I was thinking we would do it at a special meeting so that,
you know, it's just us. We would do it in the town
community room
so that,
you know, we do it in person, actually see the folks and get to know them.
Okay, question I have for the commissioners.
I know that my schedule is pretty flexible because I'm retired.
I don't know if, you know, other folks that are still working work from home is,
you know, would it be possible to
hold a special meeting on
an afternoon and
get everybody in attendance or is that a nonstarter and we need to
hold it sometime in the evening?
Steve is the representative from
the working society.
What's your thoughts on that? I can generally accommodate
>> during
the
work week. The problem I have is I'll be traveling
the week of February 6 and also You've done it as a board.
It will have to be noted. February 25 through March
8,
I believe.
>> It was a separate group The of people seventh.
No, the eighth.
Board.
>> How about some of the rest of you guys? Scott?
Just let
me know when I'll be there.
>> Stay again, Mark. Do you need me to stay?
I
don't. I think we're in good shape.
>> You very much for your help tonight. Always a pleasure. Alright. Happy New Year all. Talk to you soon. Thank you. And by the way, that text is now in Eric's box and also in attorney Williams box as well as in yours, Jen. Okay. Thank you. Good night. Good night. Thank you, Mark. Pleasure.
Chad, it's Carol Ann. I'm
>> sorry, it's Carol Ann. I'm available,
right now, Thursdays and Fridays during the day
>> if that makes a difference for you. Okay. I don't know that it would. We didn't have anybody
other than the interview team for the last one, but
I'll think about that
>> and let you know. Thanks, Carol Ann. Okay. Mr. Chairman, I would just like to suggest
one
thing,
and that is that you consider adding one member of the Conservation Commission
to the review panel,
since conservation
is one of the main focuses
of any plan of conservation
and development.
I think Mr. Gruner
would appreciate being part of the review panel.
>> And I was also thinking that you might be part of that team, Eric.
>> If you choose to, I would be willing to. I would certainly go to the presentations,
whether
I'm a decision maker or not is up to you. Board of selectmen gave you the power to make that decision.
>> You know as a Commission yep and one of the things I need to come over and discuss with you is, I saw in the back
of the proposal
they have there are expectations
of the town
and
I want to make sure we're clear on
our ability to provide and meet those expectations.
Understood. So, we'll
be talking more about that.
Leigh Ann, did you have any input on that one way or the other?
>> Just my schedule is fairly flexible.
I know, Jed, these
meetings work out well in a Zoom environment, which I think has been your preference for a while. So, if you'd rather do it that way, I have no problem with not
you know, seeing these people at an in person meeting and just having a Zoom meeting.
>> Okay, so I do think there's,
you know, one of the things that
lacks in a Zoom meeting is that ability,
you know, to
have a conversation with somebody, get to know them a little bit, and
that sort of thing. So I would like it'll be, you know, a small group of people, you know, the
six or so of us that
are
talking to them and, you know, they'll bring one or two guys over. So,
you know, there's eight of us spread around in the community room. I think that's a pretty safe environment.
Okay, let me work on some dates. I heard a willingness to go in an afternoon. I'll
look at the town schedule to find out, you know, when the community room's available and
see if we can reach out and
I will
pick some dates, run them by the commission members,
see if we can get a consensus on that before I go out and ask the
responders
what their availability might be. I think they'll work pretty hard to
come in and whatever date we pick for them to show up.
Okay, next item up is
whole business.
Jim, you want to,
tell us what you know about that?
>> I did get a letter from Chris Bell today.
It was not posted
on the website,
but if
Caroline, are you able to
to put that up on the screen?
>> I I didn't get the attachment in your email. I only got
K. The information about the,
the notice.
>> Okay.
Alright. Yeah. Chris Bell indicated that
he okay. A lot of work has been done.
A lot of the grading has been done. It's substantially complete.
Like, he
proposes to do finished grading,
go back into that hill where where the
material had been removed,
go back.
I couldn't pin him down on the exact
number of feet, but go back far enough so that he can close that hole up
and go to the left of the opening.
It's well within well outside the wetlands review area.
Or well
outside the it's approximately a 195 feet
currently.
So that shouldn't be an issue.
And hay we'd hay and seed it. This is only the next two weeks.
At that time,
we'd get finished grades
from a, an LS,
and
that's pretty much it.
So we're looking at probably a two week time period max.
And I would
it does appear that the
site
does drain in accordance with the plan, but I'd like to I will verify that when I have
when it is complete
and when I have the the as built, which will show the
the site without the drainage
basin,
etcetera.
That's about it. Any questions? I'd be happy to answer, or I'd like to, I would be happy to try and answer.
>> Well, your comment that you had a hard time getting pinning him down on what he was doing
with the hill,
you know.
I think we were all surprised when we saw the big carve out in the hill,
which wasn't in accordance with the plan.
And I think, you know, there's a lot of right answers.
We just like to know
what he plans to do so that if it's something outrageous, we can say, no, we don't like that. You know, that's not what you agreed to do. And that's what we're having a hard time
getting him to tell us.
You know, what is he going to do back there?
>> He's going to use the material
towards
on the left hand side of that mound, the mound that's exposed,
and go back approximately fifty, fifteen feet
in order to close it up and, and have an angular repose that, that
will stabilize the mound.
>> Okay.
And we're still looking for, you know, an as built Yes. As done, you know, signed by a professional
engineer that says the elevations are
correct per the plan and all that stuff. It'll be signed by an LS, licensed surveyor. Okay,
very good. Yep. Any other questions for Jim on the gravel pit?
Okay.
Next item up, approval of the meeting minutes from 12/19/2022.
And I'll make a motion to approve the minutes from December 19 regular meeting.
I'll second it. Thank you, Anne.
Any discussion
on the minutes?
>> Well, I saw my name was misspelled a number of times.
So
my name has an E.
So under
section two with members present, that's one spot.
Under new
business,
top of the second page,
the results of the vote,
It's there.
>> It's been changed under 6E, the second line. Okay. Hold on just a minute, Ann. Yep. You
said your name was misspelled.
I don't see that.
Now,
I was worried about me misspelling your name all the time because my computer used to put that little mark above the E and now I can't get it to do it anymore.
Well,
on my copy of the Oh, minute okay, I got you. It's the first name, not the yeah,
I got it. Okay, Ann, A N N E. I thought we were missing the E from Creme. And I said, no, that's got it. Okay, I got it.
>> And yeah,
the creme,
the computers always want to put the accent on the first e. It's on the second e,
but it's very hard to get a computer to do that. And also
the angle is different.
>> Okay. Well, I'm glad I'm not the only one who's technically challenged with the inability to get that whole mark up there.
>> You have to know how to get the special characters to get it. So I usually just live with it as C R E M E with I no
would like my first name spelled I
>> agree. Okay,
Carol Anne, you'll take care of that. I will address it immediately.
>> Yeah, and then on the last page, there was another spot where I had made a comment under 13 and it's in the first place there.
Other thing I had noticed in the minutes
was on the third page under,
I think about Dollar General, in the middle of the page about putting up a fence,
and it would run Route 6 to be a screen to the tree farm?
I don't know if it would be run from Route 6 or what the word was supposed to be there. It could be either to or from.
I believe it was from, Ruth says. I'll
correct it. Thank
you.
Any other comments, Anne?
Nope, that's it. Anybody else have
any other comments or corrections?
>> Yes, this is Leanne. I had this open at one point and I guess I accidentally closed it. I think it's on the second page.
I'm trying to do it from
recall
in the middle where it mentioned Steve Barnett. I think there's an e on the end of Barnett.
I think it's just, you know, b a r n e t t.
Oh,
third page.
>> Third page? Okay.
And then also, it might also be on the third page. My name is I know there's several ways to spell it. It's, capital l e I g h, and then capital a n n is a separate word.
I think that was also relatively near the end again, and I figured I could explain it in the time it would take me to bring it up again.
Okay
>> so on yes under
item 13 adjournment comments it's got Leigh Ann Hutchinson and it's LEE Vice, LEIGH.
Right.
Thus Carol has desired to have everybody spell their name that we failed miserably on tonight. But I think with what was on the screen, you got what we needed there.
>> Yeah, it takes a while to learn
this kind of thing when you're new. Yep.
>> Okay.
Any other comments on the minutes?
Okay. So
we'll do a
unanimous
consent vote on approval of the minutes as amended. All in favor, aye. Aye.
Aye.
Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
The motion passes five zero zero.
Next item up,
correspondence Jim.
None.
Next
item up, administrative reports,
enforcement actions.
>> Let's see. 12 Center Street, blighted prop property seems to be taken care of. Building
officials signed off on the on the foundation
being being, being taken
care of after after that demo. Two letters went out for trailers,
people living in trailers, one on Bear Swap, one on Times Farm, Bear Swap,
the property owner indicated
that
he had asked for thirty days to
remove the trailer
and I said that was okay. I'm confirming that in writing.
Times Farm, I also notified
a gentleman on Times Farm Road.
Got did get a call from the conservator or the fiduciary of the estate,
and
a gentleman indicated he would get back to me. I have not heard from him.
It was about
ten days ago, and I will
con I will follow-up on that.
Longhill Road, the the ongoing blight there,
I was in contact with
the town town attorney,
Dennis
O'Brien, and
he has me sending another notice, which, I will try and get out tomorrow. I I just got back from a a week away, and and it was in my
inbox
this morning.
Apparently there's a follow-up
to my last
notice
that I'm required to send,
I was not aware of.
Barnett property ongoing
Route 6 Blight.
I am continuing to work with with the owner.
I have him now providing me with copies of the manifest
for the
dumpsters
to to document
progress on that.
I do have
one application for zoning board for the next zoning board of appeals
meeting, and I expect a second. The second
being a reduction or relief from the lot size requirement
so as to
apply for a
accessory apartment, site plan for accessory apartment again at 12 Center Street.
The existing lot is shy of the 60,000 square feet
and
a variance is needed.
If that is approved, it will
require
it will have to come before the the commission for site plan review.
That's all I have.
>> Jim, did you want to
mention something about the home occupation?
I know there's
two
that I think are
brewing.
One, the one we talked about today and then the Thank other one is
you. Something on Merritt Valley.
>> Okay. I am working alright. Yeah.
Two two home home occupations. One was on
Wills Wills Road 127
and involves a
a
an armed a
gentleman that sells
guns or he processes paperwork for
firearm sales,
and it's
there's no activity on the site,
and it seemed to fall under the the
home occupation that can be signed off on
04/12 fourteen twelve a
or April,
which gives me the authority to sign off on that,
and I did.
And the second one mentioned was a problem on Merrick Valley landscaping business,
and I am working with the owner to come forward with an application.
I'll
follow-up on that and see the status of that this week.
That's all I have. Okay,
>> thank you. Thank you. You.
Our next item up is from the Inland Wetlands Water Courses Commission.
We have had no applications
through that commission
within the last month or two, so nothing to report there.
Next item up is public speak.
Once again, I see
there were a couple of people that decided
to
hang around to listen to the rest of the meeting.
Bob Hamburger, anything else tonight?
Thanks.
Nothing
else to contribute.
>> Kelly Hagerty.
Joanna Dibari.
Jordan Knight?
Maybe these people didn't all hang around.
>> Nothing
to contribute from Jordan Knight. Thanks. Okay, thank you.
Jesse Courier?
Catherine Hutchinson?
>> Yes. I'm still here.
It's
just if between
now and your next meeting,
anything comes in with regard to the gravel pit,
if it could either I get either be notified or it get posted
because I check periodically
to see what comes in,
I would appreciate it. Okay,
>> will do. Thank you, Catherine. Pardon me. This is Jesse Courier. Yep, go ahead, Jesse. I just wanted to say that cool does have its own insurance policy, and we gave a copy of it to
Eric Anderson for the town to review to make sure that it's up to their par.
>> Okay,
sounds good. Thank you.
And
I see a couple of phone numbers at the bottom. Anybody else? Anybody there want to provide any public comment? Okay,
I got two public comments just for the Commission's
information. I did brief the Board of Selectment on the January 9 about
the need for a town planner, economic development coordinator.
Improvement was noted. River East didn't
say no town planner for Andover this time. They said there's a chance. So
guess we're headed in the right direction. And
this Thursday,
I am briefing the Sustainable
Connecticut
team
on
affordable housing. So that's,
you know, part of the deal that they need for their accreditation,
and so I brief them
Thursday night.
Any other Commission
comments?
>> Ted, this is Leanne. I wasn't in the audience for the Board of Selection meeting itself, but I listened to it right after it was posted on YouTube, and I think you
spoke well. And a town planner is certainly a position that would pay for itself and then some.
So,
will go through in this budget cycle. I'm glad
Elaine spoke as well, and I'm glad Ann was able to be on
to support you. And I wanted to ask Jim, Jim, do you have any information about the CLEAR affordable housing
classes that Mark Brandt mentioned that you could send to us or tell us where to get it?
>> I do not, but
I will get it, and I'll send it out. I'm sure it's readily available.
Thank you. Leanne,
>> if you Googled
Connecticut Land Use Academy,
and the link is ucon.edu,
I think it's /clu
will get you to the appropriate page.
It's run by the University of Connecticut.
It's also an excellent, I haven't gone to their affordable housing training, but I've taken a lot of their other land use trainings
in the past, and they're fantastic.
They also have their regular basic course series for commission members
that can be taken at any time. It's an online class
that I would also encourage all of you to do because it's not as good as their in person stuff, but it's pretty good.
The other thing I was going to say is I have asked
Bill Warner
if he would speak directly with the board of selectman
so that the board of selectman
can understand from talking to an experienced planner.
What a planner could bring to the table.
We can't do it at the next meeting because Bill has a conflict,
but at one of the budget meetings, he will present to the board what the benefits of a planner would be to the town because I concur that that would be beneficial
both to the commission and to the town as a whole
to have a planner. The other thing I wanted to say is I thank you all for
listening carefully tonight
and making a good policy decision
in your role
as a land use board. So thank you for that.
>> Okay. Anybody else? Our
next next regular meeting is scheduled for February
27.
That's one week later than we would normally do due to the present stay holiday.
And I
make a motion
that we adjourn.
I'll second. Okay.
>> Thank you, Scott.
All in favor, aye. Aye. Any
opposed?
Any abstentions?
That
motion passes five-zero-zero.
And I appreciate
all of you being here tonight and
appreciate what you do for the Planning and Zoning Commission. Appreciate the help and support. So,
thank you very much.
Good night. Thanks,
Chad. Good night.